Guide to the Ernest Warren Lefever Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Ernest Warren Lefever papers
1947-1948
MS 953
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
Research materials collected largely in connection with the preparation of Ernest Warren Lefever's Ph.D. disseration at Yale University, 1956. The bulk of the papers consist of memoirs, reports, and articles about German prisoners of war who had returned from Russia. These were collected in Bremen in 1948. The remainder of the papers contain correspondence and printed matter concerning the re-education of German youth after World War II as produced by the German Youth Activities Section of the Training and Education Branch of the United States Army.
Lefever, Ernest W., 1919-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Ernest Lefever, 1951-1952.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Ernest Warren Lefever Papers are made up of research materials concerning the treatment of German civilians and prisoners of war after World War II. There is a small amount of material about the German Youth Activities (GYA) Section of the Training and Education Branch of the United States Army, established in 1945 to reorient German youth. Included are two items of correspondence with W. P. Shofstall of the GYA, notes, and statistics on United States Army assistance to German youth groups. Lefever was collecting this material for use in writing his Yale Ph.D. thesis, Protestants and United States Foreign Policy, 1925-1954: A Study of the Response of National Protestant Leaders to the Issues and Directions of the United States Foreign Policy and of the Theoretical Assumptions Which Underlay That Response (1956).
The bulk of the papers consists of materials on the treatment of German prisoners of war in Russia, which Lefever collected in Bremen, Germany, in 1948. These include first-hand histories of returning prisoners of war, reports and articles about prisoners of war, and notes and printed matter. Most of these papers are in German.
Biographical / Historical
Ernest Warren Lefever was born on November 12, 1919, in York, Pennsylvania. He was educated at Elizabethtown College, where he graduated with an A.B. in 1942. In 1945, he received a B.D. from Yale University, where he continued to study, receiving a Ph.D. in 1956. Lefever has worked in international affairs for nearly his entire life, beginning in the years following World War II, when he was a field secretary in Europe for the World's Alliance of YMCAs. Over the course of the next two decades, Lefever worked in international affairs at the National Council of Churches (1952-1954), Johns Hopkins University (1955-1956, 1960-1961), the University of Maryland (1956-1957), the Library of Congress (1957-1959), and for Senator Hubert Humphrey (1959-1960). Between 1964 and 1976, he was a member of the senior staff of foreign policy studies at the Brookings Institute. In 1976, he helped found and became president of the Ethics and Public Policy Center. He remained president until 1989, when he became a senior fellow. He has been an adviser to Presidents Kennedy and Reagan. Lefever has written, co-authored, or edited twenty books and has frequently written articles for many of America's leading newspapers and magazines.
World War, 1939-1945 -- Prisoners and prisons, Russian; Youth -- Germany (West); Europe; Germany -- History -- 1945-1955; Soviet Union; Lefever, Ernest W., 1919-; United States. Army; Yale University -- Students
- Inventory
  - German Youth Activities Section
    - Correspondence, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Notes and statistics, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - German prisoners of war
    - Histories of prisoners of war returning from Russia, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Articles about prisoners of war in Russia, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Reports on prisoners of war in Russia, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 5 - 6)
    - Reports on prisoners of war in France, England, and Egypt, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Notes and printed matter, [ca. 1947-1948] (Box 1, Folder 8)